Guide to the Blanche Matthias Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Blanche Matthias papers
1901-1983
YCAL MSS 45
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.25
(17 boxes)
The Blanche Matthias Papers consist of correspondence, reviews, poetry, short stories, clippings, photographs, diaries, scrapbooks and personal papers relating to Matthias's work and travels.
Matthias, Blanche
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Papers were donated to Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library by Blanche Matthias between 1967 and 1980 and by her estate in 1984.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in Box 17 may only be consulted with the permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
BLANCHE COATES MATTHIAS (1887-1983)
Blanche Coates Matthias, only child of Frank J. and Victoria Hudson Coates, was born in Chicago on July 16, 1887. She was educated privately and married Russell James Matthias of Chicago on July 18, 1906. Russell became president of the Russell J. Matthias Lumber Company, and Blanche developed an interest in art criticism and writing. The couple had no children and had sufficient means to travel extensively in Western Europe, the Middle East, and the Orient between 1917 and World War II.
During the 1920s Blanche Matthias served as art critic for the Chicago Herald and Examiner and Chicago Evening Post. Her poetry was published in such little magazines as All's Well, The Forum, Poetry, Prairie, This Quarter, and transition.
The Matthiases moved to Carmel, California in the 1920s and later lived in San Francisco. In 1979 Blanche Matthias donated her collection of textiles gathered on her world travels to the University of Washington. Russell J. Matthias died in San Francisco on February 18, 1974; Blanche Matthias passed away on January 11, 1983.
Scope and Contents
The Blanche Matthias Papers contain correspondence, writings, photographs, diaries, scrapbooks, and printed material documenting aspects of the literary career and personal life of the Chicago art critic and world traveler. The papers span the dates 1901-83.
The papers are arranged in five series: Correspondence, Subject Files, Writings, Photographs, and Family Papers, plus one box of Oversize material.
Series I, Correspondence (Boxes 1-3), contains both professional and personal correspondence. The collection includes a few letters concerning Matthias's work as an art critic in Chicago, most dating from the 1920s. Letters from such individuals as Alexander Greene, Max Grove, Walt Kuhn, Doris Ribera, John A. Spelman, Vincent Starrett, and Walter Ufer praise Matthias for the quality of her criticism or thank her for her remarks about their work. Others like Vernon Howe Bailey, C. J. Bulliet, and Mary F. Roberts request critical material for future publication. The publication of her poetry in little magazines is discussed in the letters of Gene Derwood, Charles J. Finger, Eugene Jolas, Dion O'Donnell, Samuel Pessin, J. H. Rutherford, and Ernest Walsh.
The bulk of the correspondence is with personal friends, many of whom moved in artistic and literary circles, including Evelyn Ames, Andrey Avinoff, Caroline Singer Baldridge, Cyrus LeRoy Baldridge, Fanny Butcher, Frederick Mortimer Clapp, Una Call Jeffers, Georgia O'Keeffe, Ruth Fuller Sasaki, Alex Shoumatoff, Carlos Suarez, and Noel Sullivan. Most of the letters discuss personal news and mutual acquaintances.
The most informative correspondents are Caroline Singer Baldridge and Una Call Jeffers. A series of letters written between 1931 and 1936 by Caroline Baldridge from Persia (Iran), Shanghai, Paris, and New York contains numerous comments on her husband's career, mutual acquaintances and literary figures, intellectual life, and politics and international relations. An April 1931 letter, for example, contains a description of life in Persia and the difficulties westerners encountered there. In Shanghai, where Roy Baldridge painted portraits of the city's ten most important financiers for Fortune magazine, Caroline reports on Japanese aggression against Mukden, the incompetence of the Nationalists, and a short visit with Pearl Buck. While in Paris she notes that they "have been a social flop--totally" because they did not drink enough, did "not loathe America," were not Communists, and were more interested in international affairs than the love lives of Lincoln Steffens and Ella Winter. Also included are comments on Richard and Alice Lee Myers, James and Nancy Pott, Gaetano Salvemini, Indian mystic Jiddu Krishnamurti, and the death of Margery Latimer Toomer. From New York City she writes about the Artists' Guild, Roy Baldridge's position with the National Recovery Administration, the Communists' manipulation of the Scottsboro Boys case, and the hypocrisy of the Communists and Fascists. She states in a January 1935 letter that "writing people [are] curiously immune to political ideas, change or idealism" and calls them "defeatists" for their lack of faith in President Roosevelt and democracy. She also writes about such people as Franchot Tone and Joan Crawford, Felix Frankfurter, Roger Baldwin of the ACLU, and mutual friends like Frederick Mortimer (Tim) and Maud Clapp.
The number of letters written by Una Jeffers to Blanche Matthias are indicative of the close relationship between the two families. The letters reveal much about the daily lives of the Jeffers from the late 1920s to 1950. Mostly written from Tor House in Carmel, California, they contain information on the poetry of Robinson Jeffers, family life, social life in Carmel, and mutual friends. Una mentions Robinson's work on Cawder (1928), Dear Judas (1929), Be Angry at the Sun (1941), and the unsuccessful efforts to perform The Tower Beyond Tragedy in the late 1930s. Several letters discuss his 1941 speaking tour and the papers include the guest list for a party given in Jeffers's honor by Blanche and Russell Matthias in New York City. In addition, the collection contains notes written for Russell Matthias by Una Jeffers on Ireland, probably dating from the time of the 1929 trip of the Jeffers, a description of their house written in 1931, and numerous references to children Donnan and Garth, particularly during World War II. Other letters mention friends and celebrities who spent time in the Carmel area, including Bennett Cerf, Charlie Chaplin, Tim and Maud Clapp, Muriel Draper, Mabel Dodge Luhan, Edna St. Vincent Millay, John Steinbeck, and Noel Sullivan. Additional information about Robinson Jeffers and the Jeffers family can be found in the correspondence of Frederick Mortimer Clapp and Noel Sullivan.
The papers contain seven folders of Georgia O'Keeffe correspondence. The letters are personal in nature, discussing mutual acquaintances and possible meetings. O'Keeffe rarely writes about her painting. On one such occasion in March 1952, she remarks that she loves winter and is working "on the winter landscape out the window."
Although Blanche Matthias was acquainted with Margery Latimer Toomer and Mabel Dodge Luhan, the papers do not contain any of their correspondence. Latimer is mentioned, however, in the letters of Caroline Baldridge and Zona Gale, and Luhan in the letters of Baldridge and Una Jeffers.
Other letters address a variety of subjects. Blanche Matthias long maintained an interest in oriental religion, a subject addressed by such correspondents as Andrey Avinoff, Claude Bragdon, Frederick Mortimer Clapp, Swami Chetanananda, Bernardine Fritz, Una Jeffers, Frances H. Leggett, Nancy Wilson Ross, Ruth Fuller Sasaki, and Carlos Suarez. The correspondence of Kay Boyle and Emanuel Carnevali concerns Blanche's monetary support for the Italian writer. James H. Pott, son of an American doctor and "a very high class Chinese woman," discusses his life as headmaster of St. Paul's High School in Anking, China, his activities, and his marriage to "a charming chinese lady." Caroline Baldridge's unfavorable characterization of Nancy Pott is found in a 1932 Paris letter. Dale Kramer wrote for information about Tennessee Anderson and the Chicago literary scene during the 1920s, while Laurie Lisle and Sarah W. Peters had questions about Georgia O'Keeffe.
Series II, Subject Files (Boxes 4-5), houses a variety of material on friends collected by Matthias. The Evelyn Ames files, for example, contain an article offprint, copies of her poems, newspaper clippings, snapshots, and several greeting cards. The material on Frederick Mortimer Clapp includes information on gnostic sects, typescripts of poems, a review of one of his books, and memorial tributes, while that on Charles J. Finger includes copies of his publications and several issues of All's Well, the little magazine he edited in the 1920s. The Georgia O'Keeffe files hold exhibition catalogs, articles and newspaper clippings, and reproductions of her paintings; those of Roy Baldridge contain drawings and Christmas cards.
Writings> of Blanche Matthias are found in Series III (Box 6) and Oversize (Box 16). The most significant writings have been mounted in two scrapbooks. The first (Box 6, folder 162) holds book reviews, exhibition reviews, poetry, articles, and a short story, "The Guardian of the Pagoda," published between 1921 and 1936. The second scrapbook (Box 16, folder 272) contains copies of articles published in the Chicago Herald and Examiner in 1922-23 and The Chicago Evening Post Magazine of the Art World in 1925-31. They concern the Chicago art scene in general and such artists as Andrey Avinoff, George O. (Pop) Hart, Walt Kuhn, Georgia O'Keeffe, Alfred Stieglitz, and Stanley Wood. There is also a copy of The Wish to Sing, a collection of poems privately published by Matthias in 1974.
Photographs, Series IV, are housed in Boxes 7-12. The series consists of seven photograph albums of three trips taken by Blanche and Russell Matthias between 1917-22 and three boxes of loose photographs, many of which were taken during their 1919-20 world tour. The first two albums document the Matthiases 1917 journey to the Philippines, China, and Japan. Among the specific locations photographed are Manila, Pagsanjan, and Surigao plus the islands of Cebu, Luzon, and Mindinao in the Philippines; Canton, Hangchow, Nanking, Peking (Beijing), and Shanghai, China; and Kyoto, Miya-jima (Itsuku-Shima), Nagasaki, Nara, Nikka, and Tokyo, Japan. Another three albums contain 1919-20 photographs of Japan, China, Singapore, Java, Burma, India, Ceylon, Egypt, Italy, and France. The last two albums hold photographs taken on a 1922 trip through the Mediterranean to Greece and Egypt. Although many of the pictures are of typical tourist scenes which sometimes include Blanche and Russell, the albums also contain photos of friends and the peoples of the countries they visited. The bulk of the loose photographs (Boxes 10-12) are of sites in East Asia, India, the Middle East, and Western Europe. The series also contains postcards and photographs of friends.
Series V, Family Papers, is alphabetically arranged by subject and contains travel correspondence, diaries, illustrated cards, memorabilia, passports, ship passenger lists, and a variety of other papers. The correspondence consists almost exclusively of letters written by Blanche Matthias during her travels, plus a handful of letters by Russell and a few letters of introduction. Blanche did not possess great descriptive skills, but it is possible to glean useful information from the letters. In a March 30, 1917 letter, for example, Blanche discusses prostitutes, gambling, and opium in Macao, and the filth, smells, and crowds in Canton. The letters of the 1919-20 world tour contain numerous references to friends like Cyrus LeRoy Baldridge and James H. Potts, plus descriptions of a cholera epidemic in Shanghai, a typhoon in the South China Sea, the beauty of Java, and a luxurious train ride from Rangoon to Mandalay. On their trip through India between November 1919 and February 1920, they visited Darjeeling, Calcutta, Benares, Agra, Delhi, Lahore, Peshawar, the Khyber Pass, Jaipur, Bombay, Madras, Trichinopoly, and Madura. Blanche discusses such subjects as Hindu burial ceremonies, Muslim hatred of the British, the terrible trains, and a camel caravan. The trip concluded in Italy and France, where Blanche writes of strikes in Naples, the bad manners of Italian opera goers, the devastation at the Italian front, gambling in Monte Carlo, and a visit to Belleau Wood. A final group of letters describes a summer 1938 trip to Great Britain, the Netherlands, and France.
The series also includes diaries for four overseas trips, the bulk of which consists of typescripts of existing correspondence. In addition to duplicate material, however, new information is provided for the 1917, 1937, and 1938 trips of the Matthiases. A 1917 diary reports on the worsening of relations between the United States and Germany and American entry into the war, sights in the Philippines, and a Chinese theater performance in Shanghai. The 1937 and 1938 diaries include typescripts of several letters not found in the correspondence. Several 1938 letters, for example, contain references to the foreboding in England and France over the possibility of war.
Other items in Family Papers include illustrated cards collected by young people in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, memorabilia from travels in the Far East, passports and international drivers' licenses, and a group of ship passenger lists.
One box of Oversize papers contains material from Series II, III, and V. The most important item is a scrapbook of Blanche's newspaper articles covering the period 1922-31.
Drawing; Little magazines; Women art critics; Women travelers; Carmel (Calif.) -- Social life and customs; Chicago (Ill.) -- Intellectual life; China -- Description and travel; India -- Description and travel; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life; Christmas cards; Greeting cards; Photographs; Art critics; Ames, Evelyn, 1908-1990; Avinoff, Andrey, 1884-1949; Baldridge, Caroline Singer; Baldridge, Cyrus Leroy, 1889-1977; Bragdon, Claude Fayette, 1866-1946; Butcher, Fanny, 1888-1987; Clapp, Frederick Mortimer, 1879-1969; Finger, Charles Joseph, 1869-1941; Gale, Zona, 1874-1938; Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962; Jeffers, Una, 1884 or 1885-1950; Kuhn, Walt, 1877-1949; Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1906-2001; Matthias, Blanche; Matthias, Russell James, 1883-1974; O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1887-1986; Sasaki, Ruth Fuller, 1892-1967; Jeffers family
- Correspondence, 1916-83; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains alphabetically arranged correspondence. Unidentified letters are placed at the end of the series.
  - Ahmed, Syed, 1920-21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ames, Amyas, 1978-82 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ames, Evelyn, 1963-83, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Anderson, Tennessee M. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Avinoff, Andrey (Adya), 1935-48, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Avinoff, Andrey: transcripts of letters (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bailey, Vernon Howe, 1922, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Baldridge, Caroline Singer, 1929-36, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Baldridge, Cyrus LeRoy, 1948-79, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Barthélemy, A., 1922 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bissell, William T., 1931 Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bokum, Fanny Butcher
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Fanny Butcher
  - Boyle, Kay, 1927 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bragdon, Claude, 1928-38 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bulliet, C. J., 1926, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Butcher, Fanny, 1962-82, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Butcher, Fanny: copies of letters, 1966-78, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Byne, Mildred and Arthur, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Carnevali, Emanuel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chetanananda, Swami, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Clapp, Frederick Mortimer (Tim), 1934-70 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Derwood, Gene, 1922 Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Evans, Evan, 1925 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Finger, Charles J., 1921-24, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
  - Forbes, M. D., 1922, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Forum, 1937 Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Fritz, Bernardine Szold, 1978, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Fujita, Jun, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Gale, Zona, 1928-37, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Goldberg, Jules L., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Greene, Alexander, 1923 Mar 26 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Grove, Max, 1922 Dec 6 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Hansen, Oskar J. W., 1940-65, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Hart, George O., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Henry Harrison, Publishers, 1932 Feb 15 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Higginson, Emily, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Hollander, W. K., 1923 Jan 31 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Houston, Kenneth, 1933 Aug 14 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Hughes, W., 1922 Apr 22 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Jeffers, Garth S., 1916-77 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Jeffers, Una Call, 1927-50, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 47-58)
  - Jolas, Betsy, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Jolas, Eugene, 1928-42 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Keene, Willard, 1933 Jul 10 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Kishadden, Peggy, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Kramer, Dale, 1963-64 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Kuhn, Walt, 1924-29, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Landau, Rom, 1937 Sep 8 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Larsen, Marie C., 1910, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Leggett, Frances H., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Lewis, Wilmarth S., 1975 Dec 10 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1944-68, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Lisle, Laurie, 1978, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Mason, Charlotte, 1923-25, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Monroe, Harriet, 1932 Oct 1 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Morden, Irene and Bill (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Nerden, Minnie C., 1923 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - O'Donnell, Dion, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1926-81, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76-82)
  - Orage, A. R., 1924-25, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Pessin, Samuel, 1923, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Peters, H., 1930 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Peters, Sarah Whitaker, 1980-81 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Polachek, Victor H., 1923, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Pott, James H., 1919-21, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Pott, William S. A., 1919 Sep 29 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Proody, Harriet, 1922 Nov 17 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Ribera, Doris, 1923 Jan 10 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Roberts, Mary F., 1924-25 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Ross, Nancy Wilson, 1970-82 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Rutherford, J. H., 1933 Aug 29 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Sasaki, Ruth Fuller, 1953-67, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 95-96)
  - Shanker, Uday, 1938, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Shoumatoff, Alex, 1976-82, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Shoumatoff, Elizabeth Avinoff, 1933-73, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Spelman, John A., 1923 Feb 7 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Starrett, Vincent, 1923 Nov 23 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Sterba, Antonin, 1923 Jan 27 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Suarès, Carlos (Joe), 1971, 1975, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Suarès, Nadine, 1937-82, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Sullivan, Noël, 1937-54, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Sweeney, James Johnson, 1954-77, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Sweeney, Laura, 1977, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Sweeney family, 1969-70 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Tagore, Protina, 1921 Mar 20 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Thurman, Howard, 1976, 1978, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Tucker, Gertrude E., 1924 May 13 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Tweeddale, Irene, 1949, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Ufer, Walter, 1923 Mar 8 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Van Hansen, Mary, 1929-30 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Villiers, Edward, 1922 Oct 22 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Walsh, Ernest, 1925-26 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Watson, Forbes, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Wentz, Carl N., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Whitell, George F., 1923 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Williams, Oscar, 1922, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Williamson, Lovell V., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Winter, Paul, 1982 Jan 14 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Woodcock, John, 1980 Sep 12 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Unidentified, 1947-81, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 121)
- Subject Files, 1921-82; Series II; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  Series II holds material concerning acquaintances and friends and is alphabetically arranged by surname.
  - Ames, Amyas, 1976, 1981, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Ames, Evelyn, 1963-80, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 123-24)
  - Avinoff, Andrey, 1936-49, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - Baldridge, Caroline Singer, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Baldridge, Cyrus LeRoy, 1968-77, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 127-28)
  - Butcher, Fanny, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Clapp, Frederick Mortimer, 1934-70, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 130-31)
  - Finger, Charles J., 1921-25, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Fujita, Jun, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Hansen, Oskar J. W., 1956-66, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Jolas, Betsy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Kuhn, Walt, 1923-49 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Landau, Rom (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Lindbergh, Anne Morrow (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1931-82, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 139-43)
    See also: Oversize, Box 16, folders 286-87
  - Ross, Nancy Wilson, 1971-82 (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - Sasaki, Ruth Fuller, 1958 May 26 (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Shanker, Uday, 1938, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - Shoumatoff, Alex, 1982 Jul 11 (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Shoumatoff, Elizabeth Avinoff, 1949-80, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 148)
  - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1922-26 (Box 5, Folder 149)
  - Sweeney, James Johnson, 1943-64, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 150-51)
    See also: Oversize, Box 16, folder 288
  - Suarèz, Carlos, 1970, 1978, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 152)
  - Tagore, Rabindranath, 1938, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 153)
  - Thurman, Howard, 1979, 1981, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 154)
    See also: Oversize, Box 16, folder 289
- Writings, 1921-81; Series III; 1.5; (1 box)
  Writings consists of alphabetically arranged articles, poems, and one small book, plus two scrapbooks of newspaper clippings.
  - "Artists: Be Yourselves," Northwest Arts, 1981 Jun 25 (Box 6, Folder 155)
  - "Katherine Dunham," Opportunity: Journal of Negro Life, 1941 Apr (Box 6, Folder 156)
  - "Purity" (poem), All's Well, 1924 Nov (Box 6, Folder 157)
  - "Roerich's Fancy" (clipped poem), All's Well, 1921 Jul (Box 6, Folder 158)
  - "Stieglitz Showing Seven Americas" (photocopy), Chicago Evening Post, 1926 Mar 2 (Box 6, Folder 159)
  - "Unknown Great Ones" (photocopy), The Women Athletic, 1923 Jun (Box 6, Folder 160)
  - The Wish to Sing, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 161)
  - Scrapbook, 1921-36, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 162)
    See also: Oversize, Box 16, folder 290
- Photographs, 1917-50; Series IV; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Series IV is divided into three subseries: Albums, Places, and People and Objects. Albums are chronologically arranged, while the other two subseries are alphabetically arranged.
  - ALBUMS
    - China and Japan: handcolored by Blanche Matthias, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 163)
    - Far East, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 164)
    - World tour, 1919-20 (Box 8, Folder 165-66a)
    - World tour, 1920 (Box 9, Folder 167)
    - Egypt: handcolored, [1922?] (Box 9, Folder 168)
    - Mediterranean and Egypt, 1922 (Box 9, Folder 169)
  - PLACES
    - Ankor-Wat: postcard, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 170)
    - Baalbek, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 171)
    - Bali, 1930 Dec (Box 10, Folder 172)
    - Bar Harbor, Maine, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 173)
    - Bromo, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 174)
    - Burma, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 175)
    - Canada: postcards, 1929 Jul (Box 10, Folder 176)
    - Damascus, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 177)
    - Egypt, 1919-27, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 178-80)
      - Postcards, 1930, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 181)
    - England: postcards (Box 10, Folder 182)
    - France, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 183)
    - Germany: postcards, 1927, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 184)
    - India, 1919-20 (Box 10, Folder 185-86)
    - India, 1919-20 (Box 11, Folder 187-89)
      - Postcards, 1920, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 190)
    - Indonesia: postcard, 1929 Dec (Box 11, Folder 191)
    - Innsbruck, Austria, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 192)